Yeah,
hello.
You tell Provost Corcoran
to get off my case.
Oh, this is Provost Corcoran.
I was just saying I'm working
on case, the case expressions.
Yes, I will give, yes, yes, sir.
Okay,
okay, thank you, goodbye, sir.
Welcome back to module nine.
We just finished views, now
we go on to case expressions.
If you're feeling like this,
then maybe exit out of this
video and work on a different
class but if you're feeling
like this let's continue on.
Case Expressions. So what
is a case expression?
Well by definition a case
expression lets SQL return
different values based
on different conditions.
It sounds a little bit complex
but when you see a simple example
hopefully it will make more sense.
So here's an example we're selecting
the first name and the GPA and
then we have a case expression.
Now the case expression examines
different conditions if the
condition is grade point average
over 3.5 or the condition is GPA is
greater than 2.0. It's like an
if statement but if statements in
SQL, you can see the third bullet
point, SQL if statements are
determined control structure. In
case expressions, they just return an
expression. And that expression
or value would be, if the GPA is
greater than 3.5, then the output
for a new column will be honors.
When the GPA is greater than or
equal to 2.0, then the response
in the new column will be good
standing. And then we have the
else part of a case expression,
and that's like the safety net. If
it doesn't fit any of these
criterias, in this case below a 2,
it will say academic warning. And
then the other parts of it are
simply end as, and this will be
the name of the new column. So
this is effectively how we create
an alias. So to summarize, it's
really like a flow chart. That
flow chart looks at different
conditions, and then it provides
values based on those conditions.
We have the safety net and then
end as the alias. One thing to
keep in mind is the first condition
that is true stops. So if we had
these two case expression when
statements switched around, if you
had a 4.0, it would first evaluate
this one had they been switched,
and it would have said good
standing instead of honors. And
so that's another important part
of case expressions. We're going
to run case expressions in two
different ways. One is called a
simple, and I refer to that as a
type one, and the other is type two,
called a searched case expression.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at both. For this business
challenge to cover case expressions,
Polly is giving a presentation,
and she currently has information
about majors, including accounting,
marketing, finance, but she
wants to create another column that
can provide a little more insight
into the students. What she would
like to do, and Eric, the IT
CIO, said no to creating any new
columns. So Polly, what she'd
like to do is create that extra
column. It will just be temporary,
but the extra column will indicate
who the advisor is for accounting,
marketing, finance, and MIS. So
in this case, we have a situation
where we have some conditions,
and based on those conditions,
we want to provide values to a
new column. So to help Polly solve
her challenge of wanting to add
that extra column and providing
additional information, a type 1
case expression will be perfect.
So type 1 is also considered simple.
It involves examining a condition
and these conditions can be numeric
or they could include a word like
risk or a column like risk and then
based on those conditions we can
provide output of value into the new
column. Now, the benefit of case
expressions, one, you don't have to redesign
the entire database. That's where
the CIO said, nope, and we can
create that column. And then the
output is based on a set of rules that
you would determine. We'll be using
the university data set for this video.
The data that you have in your
tables may differ than what I have in
my tables, but the concepts will
still be the same. In this case, to
solve Polly's challenge, we want to
identify this major column for our
case expression. That'll represent
the condition, and then we'll create
that new column based on our case
expression. So let's go ahead and get
started. We'll type in select, and
in this case, let's just say major.
That's what we're
looking at. I'll add the
comma, and then we'll
start our case expression.
And to make it a simple case expression,
again, this is where I'll include major
as the comparison column. We then
go into the when-thens, so when,
and in this case we'll put
accounting, then, and this is the
expression, so this will be Heinz
is the advisor for accounting.
When, and I have a few others, let's say
finance, then the advisor is Holland.
And I'll just put those
two for now. A third one
is let's go ahead and put
in the else statement.
These are the only two
we're going to analyze.
We have MIS and data analytics and
I think finance, no, not finance,
marketing in there as well. but
otherwise we'll just say unknown we just
don't know who that is so that's
another piece of the case expression
and then I'm going to couch it going
out one level and including end
if I don't include the as I don't
have the name of the column we have
another problem coming up where
we don't use as because it's in
the order by we'll get to that in
the next video but in this case we
can end as and maybe we'll call
this department advisor and then
finally and this is something students
sometimes miss on the exam too
you're so focused on the case
expression that you forget to indicate
that you do need to include which
table or which table or tables
I guess this is coming from in this
case will indicate this is from
the student table let's go ahead
and run this code and as you can
see we've solved the problem that
Polly had where we have a new column
and then we indicate that which
advisor is related to that particular
column and so for your practice
item Kia blue blue number one
go ahead and pause the video and
recreate what we just discussed and
this is an example of what your
output could look like again you might
have a different looking data set,
but in this case, we've created this
new column using a simple case
expression. One nice thing about having
AI available to you is if you have a
very repetitive process, for instance,
this case expression, you may be
able to find a quick workaround.
Here's an example. We indicate that
when a description of an activity is
odd, one, three, five, you can see
that it's always offered in the fall
and anytime that it's even two four
six it would always be offered in
the spring and this would be fine
except the challenge is what happens
if you now have a thousand of these
to do it follows the same simple
principle even and odd numbers but you
have so many to do and so one of the
nice things with ai you can ask for
solutions some of you are familiar
with the mod operator, and in this
case, we can use the mod operator.
Here's an example of how
it would look. Select case
description comma, and
then we have the case, and
now our case, what we're
indicating is activity ID,
which is showing that it is a simple
case expression, case and then
activity ID, but then we're using
the mod operator too, and effectively
with mod, we're looking for is
there a remainder, yes or no. If
there's no remainder, then we know
it has to be spring. If If there
is a remainder, then it's got to
be fall because it's an odd number.
Moving on to type 2 or
search case expressions.
Take a look at this one and see if
you can tell what the difference
is between the type 1 and the type
2, if anything stands out to you.
And one thing would be, in the select
description, we have the comma.
We still need the comma, but notice
for case, we don't have anything.
We go right into the win
statement. And what this does, it's
searched, it's advanced, type two,
it allows you to use a little more
flexibility with the operators,
greater than, less than, less than,
equal to, and so forth. So in this
case, it's suggesting when the
minimum age is greater than 19, then
20s. And when minimum age is greater
than 12, which would move you
right up to 19, then you must be in
the teens. otherwise we have
just a baby and then we end it as
searched and then from the activity
table and if you remember from the
original example on grade point average
the order of the case expression
mattered because if we had put
the 2.0 grade point above the 3
.0 then somebody with a three point
would get the response of a 2.0
grade point average this is the
same thing if we moved minimum age
above the 19 if we move the minimum
age is greater than 12 then if
you're 27 years old, the result
would be, is this person greater than
12? Yes, and they would be labeled
as teen. So just like the original
case expression example, you want
to be very careful to make sure
that the order of your case expression
accurately depicts the goals
that you're trying to accomplish
for this particular type of search.
Let's take a look at a sample
problem that's easily solved using a
type 2 or search case expression.
In this particular situation let's
assume that we have some scholarships
available for non-traditional
students and by non-traditional we just
mean and your data might be different
you might have if you're following
along for a blue track you
might just have to put in some dates
that fit your particular data set.
Traditional versus non-traditional
we're saying anybody born
before 1991 they would be considered
a non-traditional student.
Well let's go ahead and
see what we can do with
a searched case expression.
So we can say select
first name last name and
how about date of birth.
We won't include excuse me we
will include a comma and we
will include the column that
we're interested in for our
case but we include those
columns down below. We still use
our wins, and in this case
we could indicate when the
date of birth is less than,
and let's put a year in, 1991,
we use year and, excuse me,
year with a dash, hello, 1991,
let's put 01 and 01. And we
include this in quotes. If If we
don't, one of the problems is
SQL may be trying to take 1991
minus one minus one, and so
that's why we put these dates
in single quotes. When we have
that, we need our whens and
thens, so then we can put, this
would be a non-traditional.
Otherwise, then they must be traditional.
And then we'll close
this off with end as.
We'll put student type.
And then I tend to forget it.
Focused on the case expression, we forget
what table it is and
from the student table.
Let's go ahead and run this.
1985 would be a non-traditional.
1990 is non-traditional. But
then when we get to a 1994, it's
traditional. And keep in mind the order
of operation in which SQL reads. It
reads the select statement second
to last only before order by. If
we wanted to get rid of all of the
traditional students in our where
clause, we would have to not refer
to the student type. We would have
to say where and then put the
formula in again where the date of
birth is either greater than or less
than in order to solve that problem
with the WHERE clause, because
again, the SELECT statement alias
can only be used in the ORDER BY
because it's the last column read.
All right, we've done a simple
and a search. Let's take
a look at these two examples,
just comparing the two.
We have the case minH, so we know
this is simple. We have the case
with nothing, they both have commas.
But in this case, you would have
to say 22, then 20s, 21, then
20s, and so forth, in 23, 24, 25.
Where in this case, you could say
where it's greater than, in this
case, probably or less than 30, of
course, than they're in their 20s.
Otherwise, teens or just a baby.
In this one, the same thing. When
19, teens. When 18, teens. When 17,
teens. And so you have to create
a lot more rows, wins and thens
if you're using a simple one for
this particular use. Now, the use
to solve Well, Polly's problem
was simple when accounting finance,
so when you're using columns that
have character data, the simple
is typically an easier one to use.
And that concludes this brief
presentation on case expressions.
You'll have plenty of time to apply
these two types of case expressions
during the lab. And please tune
in for the next video. The next
video is brief on using a case
expression in the order by clause, and
this question is on the exam. You'll
know exactly what it is before
you get there. Have a great day.
We'll see you in the next video